will TV be the death of us
[Music]
welcome immortalites to another round of
the book reviews my name is Kyron host
of the mere mortals podcast but also
this one where I dive deeper into the
books that I'm reading to give you the
juicy information that is within to
extract some themes you might not have
thought about and to also look at the
difference between prit and TV indeed we
do have amusing ourselves to death
public discourse in the age of Show
Business by Neil Postman so this book
was originally published in 1985 and the
version I have here is the 2005 updated
Edition with a forward by his son Andrew
Postman and it's 163 pages in length
took me about four hours to get through
in total because it is kind of dense the
information that is contained within
essentially it is an argument of why TV
as a medium lessons rational discourse
and ultimately is a bad trade-off for
society and in particular he is focusing
here on American so the United States
Society it is split up into two parts
with neither of these being named but
the first part is really dealing with
the different mediums themselves so
print versus TV and I guess even getting
into the spoken word
and I guess whether the information
coming from these is quality and or
useful and so it is very past looking
it's looking at how did things used to
be in the past versus kind of where
we're getting up to nowadays so some of
the chapters in here are the medium is
the metaphor typographic America
meteorous epistemology the peekaboo
world it's really looking at these
things the second is more of a how it's
affecting the current society and in
particular portions of this so some of
the things in here are the age of Show
Business Shuffle off to Bethlehem
teaching as an amusing activity so I was
looking at things like politics religion
teaching advertising how it is affecting
us as humans and how TV in particular is
degrading the experience of I suppose
being a human in some certain cases or
at least in terms of information and
understanding so who was Neil Postman
well he was American born in New York
City I believe where at least he lived a
lot of his life there and he lived from
1931 to 2003 so he actually has missed
out on a large portion of what has been
happening in the last 30 years he was I
suppose a technophobe if you want to be
kind of a person who didn't like
technology for sure with caveats to this
he wasn't a hardliner and this book was
based originally on a talk at a book
fair that he did in the year before 1984
which was all about Huxley versus Orwell
so the two great I suppose dystopian
novels of the of the 20th century this
being Brave New World in 1984 1984 my
favorite book of all time
and he's really focusing about okay how
this is actually we're turning more into
the Huxley Brave New World type of deal
rather than the orwellian Draconian type
one so uh just a little interesting
piece of info there I'm going to get on
to the First theme and this being the
medium the way information is conveyed
so one of the title chapters is the
medium is the metaphor and this is a
slight play on words of something we
might have all heard before which is the
medium is the message and what this
basically is is it's saying that the
medium itself so in this case we'll just
use something like the spoken word or TV
or written text or even things like
pamphlets or books and you can get more
granular and Niche with it uh the medium
is itself is is what is being conveyed
that is what it means so the message is
somewhat uh dictated by that and then
also the medium dictates what it
contains and so uh an easy way of
thinking about this is
TV is inferior to print for for some
certain types of discourse and things
like smoke smoke signals which the
Native Americans used to use you're not
going to have a philosophical Treatise
contained within that it's impossible to
to have that amount
of of detail the meaning being conveyed
through smoke signals we can also look
at things like juries they are not
allowed to write down what certain
people are saying during the actual jury
and have transcripts of that because
when you have that in front of you the
meaning of words of what people are
saying can actually change dramatically
and so that's actually part of the the
law in the legal system so we see okay
the medium itself and the metaphor that
it contains
and this is kind of just really
examining okay the the message and the
medium the metaphor they're all kind of
combined and certain aspects of
Television versus print are going to
change and and I think we could all
probably agree on that
now what are the things one of the
things that matters with this is truth
and and how do they compare with truths
and he had this really interesting
anecdote here from a student who was
presenting a thesis or something like
that and they were giving an oral
version of this and in they also had in
this uh as accompanying this or the oral
version was accompanying the main
written text and he had a little quote
in there which was from something he had
been told in person and then he used
that as a reference as a citation saying
As Told by the investigator in the
presence of on certain date and the
people who were judging this brought
this up and so I'll go over to here and
so he's asking why do you assume the
accuracy of a print reference citation
but not a speech referenced one so why
why is this not as valid
and so in response they say the answer
he received took the following line you
were mistaken in believing that the form
in which an idea is conveyed is
irrelevant to its truth in the academic
world the published word is invested
with greater Prestige and authenticity
than the spoken word what people say is
assumed to be more casually uttered than
what they write the written word is
assumed to have been reflected upon and
revised by its author reviewed by
authorities and editors it is easier to
verify or refute and it is invested with
an impersonal and objective character
which is why no doubt you have referred
to yourself in your thesis as the
investigator and not by your name that
is to say the written word is by its
nature addressed to the world not an
individual the written word endures the
spoken word disappears and that is why
writing is closer to the truth than
speaking moreover we are sure you would
prefer that this commission produce a
written statement that you have passed
your examination should you do so then
for us to merely tell you that you have
and leave it at that our written
statement would represent the truth our
oral agreement would only be a rumor so
this is one of those cases where we can
see okay in certain cases and by and
large you would probably say written
text can contain elements of Truth
and this is very hard to get into
because it is very easy to to lie in
books and to lie in things like this and
we can see also online in this digital
age with chat GPT just being able to
write stuff out okay just because
something is written doesn't necessarily
mean that it is closer to the truth but
I think it's when you start comparing
these things and you can look at quality
versus quantity and in this case we see
on pages 68 he's also talking about one
of the things that was happening when
the telegraph came out was there was
just this abundance of information of
news coming from all across of America
you know if you're in Chicago you could
now get information from the middle of
Minneapolis or wherever the hell it is
and so it was basically just saying you
know the investors new to the stock
market perhaps an occasional story about
crime will do it does any of these
actually affect you and and this is
getting I guess not only just from the
truth but also to how what you can do
with this information and with this
truth is it useful and so do you act on
the news cycle and it's really
interesting because he's essentially
saying that TV by and large and he's
riding this in 1985 so he had you know
just to put yourself in the television
of the 1980s 1970s is what he's really
talking about
he's he's essentially arguing the the
truth that you can find in this TV is is
not as good as you can find in other
mediums and in particular in the print
medium and that the ability to act on
this is less useful as well so do you
act on the news that you hear about an
earthquake or a tsunami on the other
side of the world
um you know maybe maybe you send in some
money to a charity
um and this is where it's getting into
some questions for myself about what he
would think about current uh TV mediums
and this is where we have things like
YouTube and not only in in particular he
was against TV which I think you can
kind of take as a
as a synonym or as a in his words would
be for video he was very much against
video whereas I would be really
intrigued to know what does he think of
how-to videos on YouTube is that a
useful medium for conveying a message
which I would argue is and fantastic
it's it's much more helpful than
something like text so a lot of what
he's talking about is really trying to
convey the message that one
the medium can change things very
dramatically which I think is pretty
easy to understand most of us would be
able to to get that and his arguments
are that by and large print is better
than the medium of television and in
this case television being video so
that's I suppose the first section of
the book the first part of it is is
wrapped up in with that the second is
now getting onto the second theme which
is amusements the seriousness of Huxley
and mindlessness and so Weiss is
seriousness important this word just
crops up constantly in this book and
it's
it's it's very much a focus on his mind
I'm going to jump now on to page 50
where I think this is his explanation of
of why seriousness isn't important so we
go to here it is serious because meaning
demands to be understood a written
sentence calls upon its author to say
something upon its reader to know the
import of what is said and when an
author and reader are struggling with
semantic meaning they are engaged in the
most serious challenge to the intellect
this is especially the case with the act
of reading for authors are not always
trustworthy they lie they become
confused they over generalize they abuse
logic and sometimes Common Sense the
reader must come armed in a state of
serious intellectual Readiness this is
not easy because it comes to the text
alone in Reading once responses are
isolated one is one's intellect thrown
back on its own resources to be
confronted by the cold abstractions of
printed sentences is to look upon
language bear without the assistance of
either beauty or Community thus reading
by its nature is by thus reading is by
its nature a serious business it is also
of course an essentially rational
activity and then he goes on to talk
more about why this rationality is is
important
and yeah essentially reading in in his
case is a proxy for rationality and it's
a and rationality is somewhat of a boon
to humanity what distinguishes us from
the animals living you know bear out in
nature having to deal with all of the
horrible things tooth claw you know the
hierarchical structure of just random
death and things like this it's
rationality and we can use this to our
advantage and arguably make the world a
better place I hope we can all agree on
that
and what he says is okay well TV affects
us and it is taking us away from this
rationality and moving us more into the
amusements so how does this crop up well
we can see this with politics where it
becomes more about the appearance of
someone and not the ideas so he gives
examples of people U.S presidents in the
past they used to be able to walk the
streets of random towns and no one would
know who they were but if you saw that
written text or you started to hear them
speech you might be able to understand
oh okay this is this person and they
Rose to being president of the United
States or whatever because of their
ideas not necessarily of their physical
appearance TV obviously has a very
dramatic impact of this and a famous
cases of Nixon versus Kennedy where
Kennedy was this you know younger more
youthful looking guy more handsome and
people who watched the debates between
Nixon and Kennedy Richard Nixon and John
F Kennedy they when they watched on TV
they would argue that Kennedy won
because he knew how to act in front of a
camera he knew how to address people he
was better looking he was more in shape
Nixon not so much he had you know shiny
didn't have makeup on he didn't do all
of these things and then people who
listened via the radio and so just the
the words that they were actually
speaking speaking thought that Nixon did
better and that John F Kennedy came off
the worse than that so you can
definitely see okay the same information
is roughly being conveyed with the
additional on the video of those inputs
and it can dramatically impact what
people think of essentially the same
thing that is happening I.E the truth so
it was the truth more true in the radio
context or was it more true in the video
context
who's to say in this case he was saying
when you're getting more into appearance
and not on ideas you're taking away from
rationality and you are becoming more
about something that is it's not
irrational but it is just a it's not as
as useful so the appearance of someone
is maybe not as useful as the uh ideas
that they propound and uh and and that
they put forth another case would be
education and so this is where it's
arguing that TV is trying to make it
more of a passive activity versus one
which is active and there's all of these
Commandments which are used on TV which
don't carry well for educating someone
and so some of the Commandments are Thou
shalt have no prerequisites so every
television program must be a complete
package in itself it can't have any
additional information before that it is
almost assuming someone needs to come in
fresh so you can't build upon things
which is how Humanity typically works we
build upon the shoulders of giants Thou
shalt not Thou shalt induce no
perplexity so in this case it's saying
perplexity putting things that are
paradoxical into the information that is
being contained in the TV medium is a
big No-No you don't want to do that that
takes away from the amusement the
enjoyment of people and so they will not
watch the TV show as much as as uh as
another one and so you can't have any
Nuance in in TV
and thou shalt avoid Exposition like the
ten plagues visited upon Egypt and so
this was one where it's saying you know
arguments hypotheses discussions reasons
refutations or any of the traditional
instruments of recent discourse turned
television into radio or Worse Third
Rate printed matter and so he's saying
okay if you want to introduce aspects of
rationality of this of good discourse
into television you're actually taking
it away from being the television medium
which is focus primarily on Amusement on
entertainment and
I don't think he would argue that
entertainment and amusement is bad
in the the widest context of is this
good or bad for Humanity I think he's
just arguing that it's gotten to a point
where TV is maybe gotten a bit too much
uh reached a bit too much power a bit
too much amusement and that it it might
be better to have more rational
discourse and more thoughtful
uh things being it being a larger part
of society
now we see this with religion as well
which is where it's turned religion into
this theater it's spectacle of of
priests and people ziplining down in
their mega churches down to the stage of
you know creating these singing concerts
of having a band up on stage and uh all
of this stuff which is makes it more
entertaining for sure but is this the
original point of the religious
experience is this getting to the heart
of the deeper meaning that can be found
and what religion is is meant to do for
people and he argues no and then finally
he also has a section of advertisements
and if you've listened to the mere
models at all you will know I'm not a
big fan of of advertisement so anything
that rails against them is um I I
usually am drawn to and so we go to here
on page 104 and 105. which I think is a
really good explanation of why the
advertisement another reason why
advertisements are unhelpful to them so
he says why then do we not think a news
uh show similarly unworthy the reason I
believe is that whereas we expect books
and even other media such as film to
maintain the consistency of tone and a
continuity of content we have no such
expectation of television and especially
television news we have become so
accustomed to its discontinuities that
we are no longer struck dumb as any sane
person would be by newscaster who who
having just reported that a nuclear war
is inevitable goes on to say that he
will be right back after this word from
Burger King who says in other words now
dot dot dot this and that is the chapter
of that title now dot dot dot this which
is getting into if you're in a a
rational discourse with someone in your
everyday life and you're talking about
something and then they just absolutely
interrupt the sentence and say oh yeah
but have you seen the latest Barbie
movie and you're talking about why your
grandmother is dying of cancer and why
you won't be able to attend this event
or do this thing
that discontinuity that jumped that
perspective change is
very bizarre and I I assume most people
have met someone crazy in their life who
kind of does something like this and it
and it's a very jarring experience
and what he's saying is that at TV
immuno immunizes ourselves to this very
very strange thing that happens because
that is what it does with the television
commercials with the changing from one
topic to the next of the new cycle all
of this plays into this uh idea I guess
of that TV is more about amusement and
entertainment which in a taken to its
logical extremes will get us into the
Huxley and type idea of the mindlessness
and so right at the end of the book he's
talking about okay why was the Huxley
and
dystopia why was that so dystopic of of
Brave New World and so he says
that we are in a race between education
and disaster and he wrote continuously
um so here we go for in the end he was
trying to tell us that what Afflicted
the people in Brave New World was not
that they were laughing instead of
thinking but that they did not know what
they were laughing about and why they
had stopped think
and yeah so this I think conveys his
thoughts laughter entertainment
amusements are not a bad thing in of
themselves but they're a bad thing if
you're not sure of why it's happening
and also if it is taking away from
rationality that you could be using in
other cases
he doesn't get there himself in this
book but I would argue that the reason
for this is something like Consciousness
and that TV and things like this and
I'll apply this to the modern context of
something like Tick Tock it is largely
based on amusements and Amusements are I
feel a a mind-numbing thing that they
kind of take away from Consciousness it
makes you more of a robot and the people
creating the content perhaps a robotic
in their nature as well and NPC live
streaming is a classic uh very recent
example of this
um so does the The Idiot Box the TV as
well the idiot box is what my father
used to call it does this promote
Consciousness do when you listen to it
well watch it do you come out of it with
a higher level of consciousness of of
rationality of understanding of nuance
or perspective
by and large probably not most shows are
not designed for that most shows are
designed to entertain and amuse so that
is his essential arguments in the two in
the in the book The Medium the message
is very important and that TV as as a
medium and a message is inferior to
print and text for Society at large
um I I want to stress that this book is
very nuanced and so what I'm trying to
convey here is is not that this guy was
railing against uh TV and you know just
shooting from the hip going like Bam Bam
Bam Bam TV bad you know I once saw a kid
watch TV for 10 hours and then he turned
into a serial killers no it's not like
anything like that so let's go to my own
personal observations and takeaways
it's a good question to ask because a
book like this especially with this
title is a somewhat provocative you know
was he a technophobe was this just an
old grumpy guy who didn't like
technology you know there's a slight
aspect of that I was reading up on him
and he did have these it seemed a
general opinion that technology was a a
bad thing I guess but and he himself he
indicted indulged in hyperbole for
example amusing ourselves to death
there's nothing about this in this book
about death there's nothing in this that
is implying that uh we're all going to
die because we listen to TV or or watch
TV and it has become more important in
our lives
um there's nothing about that so
obviously the title itself is a bit
hyperbolic uh he's somewhat hypocritical
he appeared on TV shows to promote his
book to talk about these ideas so once
again he's indulging in this thing that
he is talking against but one of the
things I do like about him was that he
appreciated Paradox and that and that uh
it wasn't an either or it was more of a
an and and so I actually watched a
snippet of him on on YouTube on on a
television and show where he was saying
you know it's not either or it's about
the Faustian trade-off sort of okay you
can get this thing you can have this
thing which will
be able to connect promote understanding
learning you can learn more about the
world you can see visual this is all the
information that you can you can't get
elsewhere but that there are trade-offs
for this and and it's important to be
mindful of what these trade-offs are
and you know this is a case where I
actually watched this I I watched a
video of him and it was a good trade-off
for me because I learned more about him
um it sure it condensed his views into a
nine minute segment of him on a TV show
but it gave me ideas about more about
his speech patterns about how he
communicated to how he thought and I
went oh I actually like this guy better
and he's not that in slight impression I
might have had in my mind of being a
tech old grumpy technophobe no he was he
was a he was a real person who uh with
additional contacts I appreciated more
about him so yeah that was that was a
kind of just nice observation where it's
it's not useful to get caught up in this
person is in this box don't it's best
not to put him or or this book in a box
I think but to understand and appreciate
some of the nuances another thing I
really liked of this was his kind of
inquisitive nature and so just jumping
here onto page 13. where he's kind of
just summarizing a bunch of things about
Plato about uh text and he was uh saying
how Plato was surmising about the
consequences of writing and so just
jumping onto the end here people like
ourselves may see nothing wondrous in
writing but our anthropologists know how
strange and magical it appears to a
purely oral people a conversation with
no one and yet with everyone what could
be Stranger Than The Silence one
encounters when addressing a question to
a text what could be more metaphysically
puzzling than addressing an unseen
audience as every writer of Books must
do and correcting oneself because one
knows that an unknown reader will
disapprove or misunderstand when you put
it in that context it is very very
strange another good book that I'd
recommend is uh uh watch out there are
snakes I think is what it's called by
Daniel Everett something like that
and this was about him going to a one of
these uncontacted tribes in the uh
Amazon jungle I believe and they had no
text and even the way they communicated
was not in the sense of I believe their
grammatical structure of their language
didn't really allow for the things the
concept of I it was always the group and
this was because it was a Tiny Tribe I
think it was 100 people or something and
so he was trying to learn the language
and how they communicated to be able to
translate the Bible funnily enough
that's one of the missionaries of one of
the the greatest linguists out there
because they had to go to all these
places in the world and and understand
the language to then be able to
translate the Bible that was their their
purpose and yeah for in this case I mean
there's probably no point of him even
translating it because it would be they
didn't even know how to read and write
so what is this strange book which is
telling me things and trying to
communicate out at me and also with this
person over here it is very bizarre and
when you look at the words on written on
a page much like if you look at
hierographic symbols it becomes very
very different and you go oh like what
is this thing how is this method and
medium trying to communicate me
communicate at me was it a person was it
an entity are they addressing me as a
person or as an entity as part of a
collective it can be very very strange
and uh
the last little observation thing I
wanted to take away was you know what
would he think and what can we do
nowadays when we have these mediums
which are even more ridiculous than the
television that he was experiencing and
it's even funny because the updated
aversion by the his son I think was
published in the early 2000s so it
didn't even have the full gamut of
YouTube videos of podcasts of just
information 100x a thousand x 10 000x of
what they were experiencing and the only
thing that I could really take that I
learned from this book was just be
mindful about it if you want to use
these things you know go nuts it's
awesome but just be mindful that every
time that you're using a tick tock or
for entertainment and and Amusements it
might be taking away from some
rationality that you could be applying
elsewhere in your life and that on the
whole this might not be great for
society would I ascribe to that I'd need
to think about about that more but it's
a it's an interesting concept
nonetheless so in summary I really love
this book it was a great book but I will
acknowledge it's only for certain people
for one you're going to need a broad
base of just general understanding
learning to start off with he goes about
Plato he talks about Bible and old
religious texts he talks about the
Gutenberg Press so you need to know
about history he'll go deeper into U.S
presidents and U.S contexts things that
are particular to that and then modern
things talking about Sesame Street
talking about you know News television
stations of popular News hosts it it's a
very wide expansive book so you need to
kind of have a pretty broad broad base
just to start off with I think you'll
like this if you're fascinated by
Communication in general so maybe if
you're in the media business if you're
into marketing and getting a message
across to people telling stories if you
are interested in language learning and
how communication can change across
various languages and various different
mediums I think these are all the sorts
of things that people who would enjoy a
book like this
if you're even interested in society and
large broad sweeps and how individuals
can change based just upon what is
happening in a society this is probably
the book for you if you're not I could
see you really hating this book because
it all it'll it'll just be
uh it'll sound too weighty it'll sound
too philosophical it won't be practical
it'll it'll just go yeah I could see
myself 10 years in the past being like
no I don't I don't like this book so
you'll need to think about a lot of
things for it is definitely a thinking
book and
um it's probably one that I will come
back to and I definitely want to read
some more from this author Neil Postman
so all in all I'm giving the book
amusing ourselves to death public
discourse in the age of Show Business by
Neil Postman and eight and a half out of
ten I loved it I really did enjoy it and
it gave me a lot of ideas to take off
into other aspects of my own podcasting
life and and things like this so that is
it for today my new model lights thank
you for joining me to the end of this
video of this medium what are your
thoughts on the medium is the message on
the metaphor on this book if you have
read it on Neil postman on being a
technophob all those sorts of things
best way of doing this is just by
leaving a comment I really enjoy the
long detailed comments that I tend to
get on this channel which is a much
nicer compared to some of the others
with which have shorts and things like
this so yeah I I really do enjoy those
and I definitely like to acknowledge you
and thank you when I do the end of my
book Recaps if you if you leave a a nice
uh thoughtful comment it's um it's
something I really appreciate if you
want to do the other things like
subscribe that that helps out the
channel as well and uh you know makes it
more accessible to other people and yeah
uh other than that I would just
recommend checking out the mere mortals
podcast uh I take a lot of the ideas
from these books and I have a
conversation so once again a different
medium with my friend Juan so the the
link for that should be appearing on
your screen and it's down below as well
reach out to me join our Discord do any
of that stuff and if you want to
monetarily help support this show I'm
never gonna have advertising in here I'm
never going to do paywalls I'm never
going to do sponsorships or anything
like that so I would just ask that if
you can do that there's a PayPal link
and then these on these podcasting apps
I also do put this out as an audio only
version you can go and and check them
out and there's um various cool ways of
of helping to support via there as well
so uh yeah I'm just gonna leave it at
that for today thank you very much for
joining me and I do hope you're having a
fantastic day wherever you are in the
world ciao for now Karen out